You found it.
This is Higher Ed Hot Takes.
And I'm Joel Goodman.
Have you listened to any
of the previous episodes?
If not, welcome.
I'm glad you're here.
Sign up for emails at higher ed Hot
takes.com if you're back for more.
Well, today's topic builds on
what I've been talking about since
episode one, so let's start here.
Whether you're thinking about
personalization or integrating AI into
your workflows, or maybe worrying that
you've been adding to the slot pile
and making your job irrelevant at the
same time, you know, whatever it is.
I want to help you reframe your thinking.
All these things come down to user
experience and service design.
Whenever I take on a web project,
here's where I don't start.
Design.
I don't start with design or content
or inspiration or features or any
of that stuff, but a lot of RFPs in
higher ed do start with those things.
They like this or that from the
college down the street, or they
wanna make sure that the website
is AI ready, whatever that means.
I know other agencies also ask for
references of questions like what
websites do you like as if copying
someone is going to produce better work?
No, we have to stop thinking like that.
Like unless your goal is to soothe a VP's
or president's ego, the only right and
reasonable place to start is with the real
people who interact with your website.
And you know what?
We live in a world where more and more
real people are being disenfranchised over
political power aspirations every day.
sounds like an opportunity to make
a difference in their lives and to
your bottom line at the same time.
But what does it mean to
start with real people?
There are a lot of different ways to go
about it, but baseline, there's a ton of
psychology work to draw on and most of
it's gonna show you that the people that
visit your website don't like your dumb
chatbots and ignore your drone videos.
Add to that psychology foundation,
real world usability studies, and
it starts to get more precise.
You discover that your audience
thinks less in terms of file folders
and strict information architecture
than they do in taxonomy and results
Sidebar here, like, honestly, the
fact that in the 2020s there are still
university websites using org chart IAs
and navigation models created more than
20 years ago is just baffling to me.
Try changing it from the inside like
I've been for the past 18 years, and
you'll figure out what else is wrong
with this industry, but I digress.
Real people.
What that means is you can't
start with what you think is
cool or what's common across this
sector and expect to get results.
You have to do the research and
that doesn't mean asking ChatGPT.
This is what I've been yammering
on about all these past few months.
Other people's data and practice
rarely works for your own
without substantial tweaking.
I don't know how many different
ways I can say this, but LLMs
are built on other people's data,
practice, content, and writing.
Their output is the lowest common
denominator of what everyone else does.
It's generic reproduced mediocrity.
Using ChatGPT exclusively for
your research takes a human
element out of the equation.
You'll never be speaking to
your audience because LLMs
don't know who your audience is.
This is a problem, and this is
my core frustration with AI hype.
Our industry is so overworked, run
down, and burnt out, that it willingly
trades its core identity for tricks.
Does that sound like anything else?
Folks, this is how Fascism
roots its way into our thinking.
When slop is good enough for us, we
have no reason to be creative anymore.
When we lose creativity, we stop thinking
deeply and critically, and when we
stop being critical of what's going on,
we allow ourselves to be subjugated.
I'm not trying to be
alarmist, but this alarms me.
When I hear friends who have been
proponents of environmental protection
turn into apologists for AI, trying
to refute the evidence with poorly
researched and sourced internet content.
I break a little bit inside.
We don't have to do this.
The owners of these companies have more
than enough money, that they're not
actually using to enrich the world.
They don't need our help
getting more subscribers.
And when I see institutions paying
upwards of a hundred thousand dollars a
year for a website plugin that provides
questionable return on investment, and by
the way is being used by a load of their
peers, rather than fixing their website's
core issues, I just shake my head.
Like my platform apparently isn't
big enough to make an impact in their
thinking, but you know, I appreciate
those of you who have stuck with me
because of this sort of truth revealing.
Friends, again, this is about a
disconnection with what makes us human.
I said it in the last episode
and I'll probably keep saying it.
We have to stop outsourcing
our vitality to machines.
We're surrounded by humans with
experiences, opinions, and deep
knowledge, at least for now, and it's our
responsibility to use that, not replace
face-to-face time with typing into a
chat box, asking an algorithm questions.
Start with people.
Ask about them and their
needs and their questions.
Use this insight to craft
great experiences for them.
Create a connection with them.
Don't ask a large language
model to do it for you.
That's lazy and disrespectful.
It, it indicates you've given up and
that you don't care about what you're
supposedly doing professionally.
I was watching an episode of Top Chef
where the finalists were teamed up with
Olympians and Paralympians to complete
their cooking challenge, and at the
end, after winning the challenge, one
of the chefs said, they asked their
partner how they stayed motivated
when they'd won so many medals.
And the Olympian responded,
it's a privilege to compete.
For me, that's the motivation.
It's a privilege to exist and to have
creative thought, to be a human being
and to be able to express that openly.
Remembering that privilege and leaning
into it is how we remember, we do
this work for other people, other
humans who may need, reminding that
it's a privilege to be where they
are too, and that that means they can
make a difference in their own way.
Every day.
All your work.
Is it for the real people that it affects?
It's a privilege you have,
but it's also one that you can
easily lose in the distractions.
I'm Joel Goodman.
You can find me on Blue Sky or
LinkedIn or visit higher ed hot
takes.com to send me an email.